These new weight-loss medications
are hailed
as game-changing wonder drugs.
But just how safe and effective
are they?
Why do most people
stop taking them
within a few months,
why does weight loss plateau,
and what happens
when you quit?
I answer all these questions
and more
in this video series on Ozempic
and other GLP-1 drugs.
"Are GLP-1 Drugs Like Ozempic (Semaglutide)
Game Changers for Weight Loss?"
The new class
of weight-loss drugs,
GLP-1 agonists like Ozempic,
have received enormous,
almost unprecedented, attention
in the mainstream media.
They’ve been called "the medical
sensation of the decade."
The business press
was practically giddy,
declaring the end
of the obesity epidemic.
The enthusiasm is shared
in the medical literature,
with headlines suggesting
they are game-changing
revolutions
in the treatment of obesity:
therapeutic-wizard miracle drugs
that are hugely effective
in the treatment of obesity.
But history is littered with
failed weight-loss wonder drugs.
Every other year or so,
an anti-obesity medication
that had been approved
to be safe and effective
has had to be withdrawn
from the market
after serious side effects
emerged.
See my video on the subject
for the whole sordid story
of how these so-called
medical magic bullets
have turned out to be blanks,
or worse.
To date, most weight-loss drugs,
despite their initial approval,
have since been
pulled from the market
for unforeseen side effects
that have turned them
into a public threat.
From "rainbow diet pills"
packed with amphetamines
that were marketed to women,
to the rise and fall of fen-phen
(which triggered catastrophic
heart and lung conditions),
history is beset
by failures to find
safe, successful
weight-loss drugs.
Aminorex was a widely prescribed
appetite suppressant
before it was pulled
for causing lung damage.
Eighteen million Americans
were on fen-phen
before it was pulled for causing
severe damage to heart valves.
Meridia was pulled
for heart attacks and strokes,
and Acomplia for psychiatric
side effects, including suicide.
Belviq was withdrawn in 2020
after it was recognized that
it may have been causing cancer
for the eight years
it had been on the market.
The U.S. Food and Drug
Administration
initially rejected it
after it appeared to cause
several types of tumors in rats,
but when a one-year human trial
showed no apparent cancer,
it was approved
and went on to become
one of the most frequently
prescribed weight-loss drugs.
But when people were actually
on it for a few years,
notably high rates of colorectal
cancer, pancreatic cancer,
and lung cancer popped up;
so, oopsey,
it was pulled from the market.
The news was met
with surprise and confusion
among obesity medicine
specialists,
who had been
prescribing the drug
to help patients
achieve and sustain
the health benefits
of weight loss.
It was particularly jarring,
because the drug was generally
regarded as being so safe,
until it wasn’t.
Or take Benfluorex,
like Ozempic,
another diabetes drug repurposed
as an appetite suppressant.
It caused hundreds of deaths,
but didn’t get pulled
for 33 years.
The drug company knew about
the risks, but covered them up.
Judges concluded
that the drug company’s priority
was systematically given to
"preserving
its own economic interests
over the safety
of the drug’s consumers."
So, historically,
anti-obesity drugs have been
kind of like cigarettes.
Like smoking,
popping these pills
can cause you to lose weight,
but at what cost?
The goal of weight loss is not
to fit into a skinnier casket.
But they don’t even work
very well.
The current crop of
approved meds includes Qsymia,
a combination of phentermine,
the phen in fen-phen,
and topiramate, a drug
that can cause seizures
if you abruptly stop taking it.
This drug combination
was explicitly rejected
multiple times
for safety reasons in Europe
but remains for sale
in the United States.
Contrave is another option,
if you choose to ignore
its own black-box warning
about a potential increase
in suicidal thoughts.
Alli, also sold as Xenical,
is the final choice.
That’s the drug
that blocks fat absorption
and causes side effects such
as "flatus with discharge."
The drug evidently "forces
the patient to use diapers
and to know the location
of all the bathrooms
in the neighborhood
in an attempt
to limit the consequences
of urgent leakage
of oily fecal matter."
All for a grand total
of just 3 percent weight loss.
All that mess to go from, like,
300 pounds (135 kg)
down to 291 pounds (130 kg).
As you can see,
older weight-loss medications
only achieved about
5 percent weight loss,
whereas the newfangled
GLP-1 agonists like Ozempic
can cause an average of...
6 percent weight loss!
Now, this is because they were
averaging the effects
of some of the older GLP-1
agonists like Saxenda or Byetta.
Semaglutide,
sold as Ozempic for diabetes
and Wegovy for weight loss,
causes about twice that.
And now, there’s tirzepatide,
sold as Mounjaro or Zepbound,
which gets you closer to what
you see with bariatric surgery.
So, while the older
obesity medications achieve
weight losses in
the 5 to 10 percent range,
the new generation of agents
are more in
the 15 to 20 percent range,
about triple what we saw
in many of the older drugs.
So, for about half a century,
there’s been healthy skepticism
about new-kid-on-the-block
obesity drugs
promising profound weight loss,
only to see one after another
fail and flop,
but today, this historical
narrative could be in flux.
How well do these new GLP-1
agonist drugs really work?
How do they work?
How long do they work?
What are
the short-term side effects?
the long-term side effects?
Are there cheaper, safer,
natural alternatives
to boost GLP-1
with diet and lifestyle?
What even is GLP-1?
I’ll cover all those topics
and more next.